<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tenants Support Forum</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tenants Support Forum</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Start here</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/start-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/start-here/</guid>
      <description>Need helpful tips and reliable information about flat-hunting in Berlin? Struggling to separate facts from myths? Open our guide and get informed!&#xA;Flat Hunting in Berlin: A Guide&#xA;One of the first things you’ll notice when looking for a flat in Berlin is how many long words and specific terms there are! To help, we have created a glossary of terms related to the German Rental Market in five languages.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monthly Forum</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/forum/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are the Mieterschutzbund and Mieterverein?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-are-the-mieterschutzbund-and-mieterverein/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-are-the-mieterschutzbund-and-mieterverein/</guid>
      <description>These are renters unions that you can join if you have a rental contract (Mietvertrag). You have to pay a small fee, but after that, you can call them for free advice and they will help you in rent disputes. We would really recommend joining one if you can.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Anmeldung?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-anmeldung/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-anmeldung/</guid>
      <description>Anmeldung is your city registration. It enables you to get a tax ID, library card, and access other services. You need to make an appointment for this at the Bürgeramt ideally within a month of arriving in Germany. You need to bring your rental contract as proof of address to your Anmeldung appointment.&#xA;If your subletter/main tenant says &amp;ldquo;no Anmeldung possible,&amp;rdquo; that is a sign that the sublet is illegal (not cleared by the landlord).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between unbefristet / befristet Mietverträge?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-difference-between-unbefristet-befristet-mietvertraege/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-difference-between-unbefristet-befristet-mietvertraege/</guid>
      <description>An unbefristet Mietvertrag is an unlimited rental contract. Normally these come with a minimum rental period, often 2 years. This means that if you want to move out before the end of these 2 years, you need to give 3 months notice and find a suitable tenant to replace you. Watch out though, because if you are renting from a private landlord, they are able to take the property back if they or a family member want to move into it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are Nebenkosten?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-are-nebenkosten/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-are-nebenkosten/</guid>
      <description>These are costs for hot water, heating and general apartment building costs. They are included in warm rent, but may increase if the gas price increases for example. They do not include electricity and internet, and sometimes do not include gas for ovens/cookers either.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is a SCHUFA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-schufa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-schufa/</guid>
      <description>A SCHUFA is a credit check obtained by not totally transparent means by a private company. You will need a German bank account (N26 is easy to get as it requires fewer documents or Anmeldung) in order for the check to occur. You often need to provide your SCHUFA certificate to prospective landlords. It costs 29.95EUR. https://www.meineschufa.de/de/ </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is ein/e Bürge oder eine Bürgin Guarantor form for people with low/no income?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-b-guarantor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-b-guarantor/</guid>
      <description>The rental guarantee is by definition a guarantee for a rental relationship. The guarantor is thus liable for the tenant if the latter does not pay his rent or the Nebenkosten or does not meet another demand of the landlord.&#xA;In addition, the guarantee for a tenant can protect the landlord against damage caused by the tenant: If the tenant breaks something in the apartment, the guarantor must pay the landlord the cost of repairing the damage if the tenant himself is unable to do so.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Indexmietvertrag?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-indexmietvertrag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-indexmietvertrag/</guid>
      <description>This type of contract allows the landlord to increase your rent in line with inflation (%) every year. This means your rent will go up annually, so it is not an ideal type of contract. The % added to the rent corresponds with the inflation increase of the previous year. The high inflation of 2023 could therefore still affect your rent in 2024. If you have already signed a contract like this, don’t panic!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Mietschuldenfreiheitsbescheinigung</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-mietschuldenfreiheitsbescheinigung/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-mietschuldenfreiheitsbescheinigung/</guid>
      <description>When you move flats in Berlin, your next landlord might ask you for a debt free certificate. This is a signed document from your previous landlord saying you have no outstanding debts to them. Wunderflats and other short term flats do not require this, which helps for people who are moving here for the first time. If your landlord doesn’t give you one, you can show future landlords the last 3-6 months of rent payments on your bank statement instead.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Mietspiegel (rent mirror)?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-mietspiegel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-mietspiegel/</guid>
      <description>This is the average rent for your area and property type. Your landlord should not charge you more than 10% over this average rent (although there are exceptions, e.g. with furnished flats, which in practice makes this quite difficult). You can check what your rent should be for your property type here: https://mietspiegeltabelle.de/mietspiegel-berlin/</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Staffelmiete?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-staffelmiete/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-staffelmiete/</guid>
      <description>This is a graduated rent which will increase over time by limited amounts i.e. 10%. It is something to watch out for, as some housing websites offer a cheap rent for 3/6 months, which then increases after that point. It should be included in your contract. If you have already signed a contract like this, don’t panic! There is still scope to negotiate - the rent increases could be illegal. Ask a renters’ union to check the contract.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the Abschlagszahlung?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-abschlagszahlung/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-abschlagszahlung/</guid>
      <description>This is a fee for the previous tenant’s furniture and fitting, that they might ask you to pay upfront if you want to rent their flat. Sometimes these can be excessively high and are essentially bribes. Currently there is not much regulation governing this issue, and furnished flats are often harder to apply the Mietpreisbremse to.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the Mietpreisbremse?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-mietpreisbremse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-the-mietpreisbremse/</guid>
      <description>This is a rent brake - theoretically it is a legal mechanism which can be used to get a rent deduction or refund from your landlord if you can prove that they are charging you significantly over the Mietspiegel for no good reason (i.e. no furniture, no renovations). If you are a member of a renters’ union, they can help you work out if you have the grounds to enact this mechanism on your landlord.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is WBS (Wohnberechtigungsschein)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-wbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-wbs/</guid>
      <description>The Wohnberechtigungsschein is the official proof in Germany that you can move into a publicly funded WBS apartment. The WBS is the document with which you can prove that you are entitled to such a subsidized rental apartment with WBS.&#xA;The legal basis for the Wohnberechtigungsschein is the § 5 Wohnungsbindungsgesetz (WoBindG) in connection with the § 27 Abs. 3 to 5 Wohnraumförderungsgesetz (WoFG) issued.&#xA;The Wohnberechtigungsschein is intended to provide affordable housing for low-income households.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Wohnungsbaugenossenschaft?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-wohnungsbaugenossenschaft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-wohnungsbaugenossenschaft/</guid>
      <description>This is a housing cooperative. There are several around the city. They offer lower rents in return for the payment of membership fees/shares, so that you become part of the cooperative. You have to apply and then you will join a waiting list. Waiting lists can be long, but if you plan to stay here long-term, this could be a good option.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does a 3 room apartment mean? (drei Zimmer)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-a-3-room-apartment-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-a-3-room-apartment-mean/</guid>
      <description>A 3 room apartment means 1 living room and 2 bedrooms. You have a kitchen (separate or an &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo; kitchen included in one of the rooms), a bathroom, a hallway. This is a 3 Zimmer Wohnung.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does cold rent mean?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-cold-rent-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-cold-rent-mean/</guid>
      <description>Cold rent (Kaltmiete) is the basic rent you pay for the apartment. This is fixed per month and you pay additional expenses on top.&#xA;Cold rent does not include:&#xA;Heating Expenses for cleaning trash Internet Electricity You pay 3x your cold rent to your landlord as the deposit. They must return it to you when you leave the apartment. If applicable, landlords can deduct charges for your apartment maintenance, fixing things, etc and return the balance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does warm rent mean?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-warm-rent-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-does-warm-rent-mean/</guid>
      <description>Warm rent (Warmmiete) is the total rent you pay for the apartment to your landlord.&#xA;Warm rent includes:&#xA;Heating Expenses for cleaning trash Warm rent does not include:&#xA;Internet Electricity </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is a furnished apartment? (möblierte)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/furnished-apartment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/furnished-apartment/</guid>
      <description>Furnished apartment includes most of the basic equipment that you require. Your rent usually includes internet &amp;amp; electricity. The rent is much higher, as you are also &amp;ldquo;renting&amp;rdquo; the furniture as well. Furnished apartments are a decent solution, when you are new to Germany. You can:&#xA;Do your city registration (Anmeldung) Rent them almost immediately, even from your home country Easier to find than an unfurnished apartment Although the rent is higher, it&amp;rsquo;s not a guarantee to get the place if you apply.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is a Kaution?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-a-kaution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-a-kaution/</guid>
      <description>This is your deposit - it should be no more than 3x your cold rent. The landlord should put it in a shared or separate account and send you proof of this. You are entitled to receive any interest accrued on it along with the rest of the deposit when your tenancy is over. Unfortunately, the landlord has up to 6 months to return it to you!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is an EBK?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-an-ebk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/what-is-an-ebk/</guid>
      <description>EBK (Einbauküche) means a fitted kitchen in your apartment. As kitchens can be really expensive, this can be beneficial.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is an unfurnished apartment? (unmöbliert)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/glossary/unfurnished-apartment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 22:21:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/glossary/unfurnished-apartment/</guid>
      <description>There is no furniture in the apartment and it will be empty. You might find a stove and a sink but that is all.&#xA;You will have to get your own:&#xA;Bed Kitchen - Probably the most expensive part Internet connection - takes a few weeks. Internet providers are not quick to setup connections, or anything really. Switch your electricity provider - Electricity is available by default, although that can get expensive Furniture - tables, chairs, lights, etc.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guide to Flat-Hunting in Berlin</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guide/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
